Guide to the International Longshoremen's Association: Reference Files Compiled by the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union WAG.055
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Longshoremen's Association: Reference Files Compiled by the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union
1921-1984, (Bulk 1950s-1970s)
1950-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union
WAG.055
5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
In 1986, the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU) de-accessioned reference files from its Anne Rand Research Library pertaining to its rival, the New York-based International Longshoremen's Association (ILA), and donated them to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University. The militant ILWU, representing West Coast longshoremen, had once been part of the ILA, but broke away during the bitter labor and political struggles of the mid-1930s. This contentious history forms the backdrop to the ILWU's amassing of extensive reference files on the ILA and its travails. The reference files include handbills, contracts, proceedings, internal documents, and newspaper clippings from the New York Times, the Wall Street Journal, the Journal of Commerce and other trade and labor papers – many of them documenting charges of fraud and racketeering on the New York City waterfront.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, 1986. The accession number associated with this gift is 1986.006.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
In 1986, the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union de-accessioned reference files from its Anne Rand Research Library pertaining to its rival, the New York-based International Longshoremen's Association, and donated them to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University. The ILWU and its reference librarian, Carol Schwartz believed an East Coast location would better serve the research needs of scholars studying Atlantic and Gulf Coast maritime history.
As historian Gary Fink has written, "Longshoremen's unions on the West Coast had traditionally carried on a volatile relationship with the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA)." (Fink, Labor Unions, Greenwood Press, 1977, p.196) Despite fluctuating fortunes of West Coast locals, and a powerful employers association that dominated the industry until the mid-1930s, western longshoremen maintained an uneasy affiliation with the ILA until its conservative president, Joseph Ryan clashed openly with West Coast militants over issues that culminated in the historic San Francisco general Strike of 1934. When militant leader Harry Bridges was elected president of the San Francisco ILA local in 1934 (and later West Coast District president) a split became inevitable. In 1937 the Bridges group obtained a charter from the CIO for the International longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, representing Pacific Coast longshoremen. In the 1940s the two unions added to their ranks while keeping a wary eye on each other, until the ILWU fell afoul of Taft-Hartley Act anti-Communist provisions. Bridges became entangled in legal battles to avoid deportation to his native Australia, and the union found itself vulnerable to raids by the Teamsters and other rivals. At the same time, in the post-World war II period ILA members became increasingly dissatisfied with their leadership, and widespread charges of corruption brought an investigation of the union by the New York State Crime Commission. The result was inconclusive, but the American Federation of Labor demanded extensive reforms; when talks with the ILA broke down the AFL suspended the union and soon chartered a rival, the International Brotherhood of Longshoremen. The fledgling IBL failed make serious inroads in ILA membership, and the ILA reaffiliated to the AFL-CIO in 1959.
This contentious history forms the backdrop to the ILWU's amassing of extensive reference files on the ILA and its travails. This collection represents an unusual glimpse of a union's serious effort to monitor the fortunes of a rival labor organization -- in this case, a rival with which it had once been affiliated.
Scope and Content Note
The International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union (ILWU) reference files on the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA) consist of 5 linear feet of "everything we could get our hands on about the ILA," according to the ILWU's librarian: handbills, contracts, proceedings, internal documents from negotiations, and newspaper clippings from the New York Times, the Wall Street Journal, the Journal of Commerce and other trade and labor papers. Of particular significance are the clippings files in Series II labeled "Crime and Racketeering" and "American Federation of Labor: Relations," which cover the proceedings of the New York State Crime Commission and the subsequent expulsion of the ILA from the AFL. Also of note are bargaining files ("Agreements, Negotiations"), files on strikes, and files on rank-and-file committees.
Several runs of serials, including the ILA's rank-and-file publication Shape-Up, have been removed from the collection and catalogued as part of the Tamiment Library.
Arrangement
Both series are arranged alphabetically by topic, and chronologically within topics.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
Series I: Subject Files, 1921-1984.
Series II: Clippings Files, 1939-1979.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Oral history interviews with Thomas Gleason, ILA President; John Dwyer, leader of the International Brotherhood of Longshoremen; Sam Madell, Rank and File leader in the ILA; and working longshoremen, Ronald and Peter Bell. All interviews were taped in the early 1980s as part of the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives' New Yorkers at Work Oral History Project. (OH # 1).
Fliers (printed matter); Clippings (information artifacts); Collective bargaining |x Stevedores |z United States.; Strikes and lockouts |x Stevedores |z New York (State) |z New York.; Contracts; Reports.; New York (N.Y.); Stevedores -- Labor unions -- United States.; International Longshoremen's Association; Ryan, Joseph.; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union; Gleason, Thomas.; Corsi, Edward.; New York (State). Crime Commission; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union
- Series I: Subject Files, 1921-1984.
  - African-American Longshoremen and Discrimination, 1942-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African-American Longshoremen and Discrimination, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African-American Longshoremen and Discrimination, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1951, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Agreements, Negotiations, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Agreements, Negotiations: Seniority, 1957-1958, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - American Federation of Labor Relations: AFL Flyers, Leaflets, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Federation of Labor Relations: International Longshoremen's Association, leaflets, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Federation of Labor Relations: International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, Flyers and Leaflets, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Federation of Labor Relations: Re-Affiliation, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Federation of Labor Relations: Seafarers' International Union Proposal, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - American Federation of Labor Relations: United Mine Workers, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bradley, William V., 1953-1961, 1967, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Code of Fair Dealing, Mar 1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Crime and Racketeering, 1945-1953, 1970, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gleason, Thomas W., 1955, 1957-1958, 1961-1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hiring: Shape-up and Hiring Hall, 1942-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hiring: Shape-up and Hiring Hall, 1955-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Longshoremen's Association: Canada, 1963-1969, 1972-1979, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - International Longshoremen's Association: Constitution, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Longshoremen's Association: Conventions, 1940, 1949, 1951, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - International Longshoremen's Association: Conventions, 1967, 1971, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - International Longshoremen's Association: Directories, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - International Longshoremen's Association Headquarters: Notices, 1937, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Local 815 (Milwaukee), Longshoremen's Voice, Mar 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Local 1291 (Philadelphia), 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Local 1419, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Local 1814 (Brooklyn, NY), 1954, 1960-1969, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Loyalty Rally: Flyer, Rally Song, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Maritime Safety Code, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National Labor Relations Board Rulings, 1954, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rank and File Committees: Flyers and Leaflets, 1941-1949, 1953-1954, 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ryan, Joseph P., 1933-1937, 1940-1959, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Shape-Up (New York ILA Publication), Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Strikes, 1945, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Strikes, 1953-1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Strikes, 1963, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Strikes, 1972, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Strikes: Board of Inquiry, 1948, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Strikes: Board of Inquiry, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Waterfront Commission, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Waterfront Commission, 1956-1960, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Waterfront Research Committee, 1938, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Waterfront Research Committee, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Work Record, Holiday Schedule, 1955, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series II: Clippings Files, 1939-1979.
  - ILA Clippings, 1939-1947 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - ILA Clippings, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - ILA Clippings, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - ILA Clippings, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - ILA Clippings, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - ILA Clippings, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ILA Clippings, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ILA Clippings, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - ILA Clippings, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - ILA Clippings, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - ILA Clippings, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - ILA Clippings, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - ILA Clippings, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - ILA Clippings, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - ILA Clippings, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - ILA Clippings, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - ILA Clippings, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - ILA Clippings, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - ILA Clippings, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - ILA Clippings, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - ILA Clippings, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - ILA Clippings, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - ILA Clippings, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - ILA Clippings, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - ILA Clippings, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - ILA Clippings: American Federation of Labor, Relations, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - ILA Clippings: American Federation of Labor, Relations, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - ILA Clippings: American Federation of Labor, Relations, 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - ILA Clippings: Anastasia, Anthony, 1952-1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - ILA Clippings: Boycotts, 1950, 1956-1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, 1940-1942, 1946-1949 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Jan 1952-Nov 1952 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Dec 1, 1952-Dec 14, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Dec 15, 1952-Dec 20, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Dec 21, 1952-Dec 31, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Jan 1, 1953-Jan 16, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Jan 17, 1953-Jan 31, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Feb 1953-May 1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, Jun 1953-Dec 1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, 1956-1959 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, 1960-1975 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - ILA Clippings: Crime and Racketeering, 1976-1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - ILA Clippings: Local 1814, Brooklyn, 1954, 1963-1969, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - ILA Clippings: Scotto, Anthony, 1963-1970 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - ILA Clippings: Scotto, Anthony, 1971-1978 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - ILA Clippings: Scotto, Anthony, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - ILA Clippings: Seniority and Hiring, 1966, 1971-1972, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - ILA Clippings: Waterfront Commission, 1953-1978 (Box 5, Folder 17)